we're continuing our discussion of how
Spinners are related to Le groups and
Lee algebras in the last video we
discussed how Le groups are continuous
groups such as the group of rotations in
3D space called SO3 with capital letters
we also found we could write the three
basic rotation matrices as exponentials
of special 3x3 matrices called generator
matrices which live in the Lee algebra
so 3 written with lowercase letters in a
fractor
font the Le group SO3 is made of 3x3
matricies where the inverse equals the
transpose and the determinant is one we
found that this group's generators in
the Lee algebra SO3 were traceless
anti-symmetric matrices and they obeyed
these commutation relations here in the
context of Lee algebras the commutator
operation is also called the Lee
bracket we said these matrices belonged
to the spin one representation of the Le
group SO3 and Lee algebra SO3 because
these matrices are used to transform
vectors which are rank one
tensors in this video I'm going to
introduce the spin zero representation
which transforms scalers and the spin
1/2 representation which transforms
Spinners this will lead us to talking
about the double cover of SO3 which is
su2 also called spin
3 in the last video I mentioned how the
complex number I can be represented as a
2x2 matrix that squares to the negative
identity Matrix in this way all
operations with complex numbers can be
written in the form of 2x2
matrices however there are many
different matrices of all different
sizes that also behave like the complex
number I and square to the negative
identity Matrix we call these different
matrices different representations of
I similarly the Lee algebra SO3 is
defined by the following commutation
relations between the three basis
generators we've already found one set
of 3x3 matrices that satisfy these
relations but we can also look for
matrices of other sizes which also
satisfy them the simplest solution we
could look for would be the case of 1x
one matrices which is the spin zero
representation one by one matrices are
just scalers with square brackets
written around them since scalers
commute with each other the commutation
relations automatically go to zero so
we're forced to set all three of the
generators to be the 1 by one zero
Matrix if we exponentiate these one by
one generator matrices exponentiate
iting to the power of zero just gives
the number one so our rotation matrices
are just the one by one identity
matrices containing a single number one
inside so we find that the spin zero
representation of the SO3 Le algebra is
just one by one matrices containing the
number zero and when we exponentiate
these we get the spin zero
representation of the SO3 Le Group which
are just one by one matrices containing
the number one we call this the spin
zero representation because it tells us
how to rotate spin zero particles which
are represented by
scalers this representation tells us
that when we rotate a spin zero particle
this is the same thing as multiplying it
by the number one in other words spin
zero particles represented by scalers do
not change when we rotate them the higs
boson and P mesons are examples of spin
zero particles
the spin zero representation is a bit
boring and for this reason we call it
the trivial representation of SO3 but
it's an important fact to know that spin
zero particles are unaffected by
physical
rotations so for the SO3 Le group we
know the spin one representation which
are 3x3 matrices and the spin zero
representation which are one by one
matrices but what about the spin 1/2
representation which would be 2x two
matrices it turns out that there is no
non-trivial 2x two representation of the
SO3 Le group the proof of this is a
little complicated and it will have to
wait until the next video but we cannot
find 2x two matrices that behave like
the SO3 rotation
group so how are we supposed to
understand spin 1/2 particles that are
represented by spinners
if we don't have 2X two matrices that
transform them it turns out we're going
to need to go on a dour and instead of
talking about the Le group SO3 we're
going to talk about the Le group su2 the
set of 2x2 matrices that are unitary
meaning the inverse equals the hermiss
conjugate denoted with a dagger and
special meaning the determinant is
one in video number 10 of this series I
talked about how su2 matrices are the
double cover of SO3
matrices when rotating a 3D Vector we
normally use a 3X3 SO3 Matrix but we can
also rewrite this 3D Vector as a 2x2
complex Matrix called a POI vector and
rotate it using a double-sided
transformation with a pair of su2
matrices that use half
angles so to transform a PO vector v
with an su2 Matrix U the transformation
law is UV U dagger however if we replace
U with minus U the two minus signs
cancel out and we end up with the same
transformation as plus u this means that
both plus u and minus U perform the same
rotation so for every SO3 rotation
Matrix R there are two su2 matrices plus
u and minus U that perform the same
rotation this is why we say su2 matrices
are the double cover of s
SO3 in video number 12 we saw that su2
was equivalent to the spin 3 group from
Clifford
algebras in video number 10 we also
showed that su2 is shaped like the three
sphere with plus u and minus U located
at opposite ends if we draw a projection
line through plus u and minus U that
projects them to the same point the
result is the SO3 Group which is shaped
like half of a three spere where if you
wander off the edge you're immediately
taken to the other
side so to explore the su2 Le group
let's look at the corresponding su2 Lee
algebra this ends up being the set of
traceless anti-h hermiss
matrices the proofs for this are almost
identical to the ones we saw for SO3 in
the previous video we used this theorem
for for a matrix a which says that the
determinant of e to the a equals e to
the trace of a since the determinant of
an su2 Le group Matrix is one this
automatically implies that the trace of
its generator Matrix must be
zero also the unitary property means U *
U dger equals the identity Matrix if we
take the derivative of both sides
product rule gives us a sum of two terms
equaling zero after a little algebra and
setting Theta to zero we get that the
su2 generator matrices must be
anti-mission meaning M dagger equals
m so let's see what traceless
anti-mission matrices look like if we
start with a general 2x2 matrix with
complex numbers Alpha Beta Gamma Delta
the traceless property means that Delta
must equal negative Alpha the
anti-mission property means the Herm
Mission conjugate version of this Matrix
equals its negative this means that
Alpha complex conjugate equals negative
Alpha so Alpha is a pure imaginary
number with no real part also gamma
equals negative beta complex
conjugate so given this su2 generator
Matrix we have a purely imaginary
complex number Alpha and a complex
number beta this translates to three
real parameters a b and c C this means
that all 2x2 traceless anti-mission
matrices can be written as a linear
combination of these three basis
matrices if you've been watching all of
this video series so far you might
recognize these as the bi Vector
matrices in the Clifford algebra
cl3 recall that the Clifford algebra cl3
has a scaler represented by the identity
Matrix three vectors represented by the
PO or Sigma matrices and three B vectors
and a tri Vector represented by the
corresponding Matrix
multiplications the 2x2 su2 generator
matrices which are traceless and anti-
hermiss are exactly the bi vectors in
this Clifford
algebra remember the Key properties of
this Clifford algebra are that the basis
vectors Square to the scalar one and
orthogonal basis vectors anti commute so
we can switch their order and get a
negative
sign so let's take the 2x2 generators of
su2 to be the three B vectors from
cl3 the subscripts on the generator
correspond to the subscripts of the two
sigmas that it is equal
to now let's look at the commutator
between gxy and gy Z if we sub in the
corresponding sigmas we can swap these
two Sigma pairs here in exchange for two
minus signs which then cancel with each
other then Sigma y^ 2 goes to 1 here and
here then we swap the order of Sigma X
and sigma Zed to get a negative sign and
we end up with NE -2 * Sigma Z Sigma X
which is -2 * the Z x
generator so using this choice of su2
generators we get these commutation
relations these factors of -2 are not
desirable but we can easily remove them
with a simple change of basis we'll
Define the G Tilda basis as the G's * -
one2 remember Lee algebra generators are
like basis vectors so we're just
reversing the vector directions and
making them half as
long with these extra factors of - one2
the commutator of any two generators is
exactly equal to the Third
generator so with this new basis we're
able to remove the factors of -2 in the
commutation
relations and I'm just going to use this
basis for our su2 generators from now on
written without the
tildas these three generators end up
being equivalent to the unit querian J
JK divided by two I showed the
equivalence of the querian and bi
vectors in video
6.1 they all obey the the same
multiplication
rules now you'll notice that these su2
Lee algebra commutation relations are
exactly equal to the SO3 Le algebra
commutation
relations so what's going on here the
two Lee algebras are equivalent even
though their corresponding Lee groups
are not equivalent remember su2 is the
double cover of s SO3 so they are not
equivalent I'll come back to to why this
is
later so we have this set of 2x2
matrices that satisfy our su2 Lee
algebra commutation relations but now
we'd like to see the actual su2 lead
group members that do the
rotations to see these Le group matrices
we just exponentiate the generators
let's compute the exponentiation of the
XY generator times an angle Theta and
see what we
get now one option would be to use the
tailor series definition of the Matrix
exponential and plug in all the Matrix
powers and end up with this Matrix as a
result this is correct but it's a lot of
work it turns out that there's an easier
way recall Oiler formula which says that
e to the I Theta equal cosine Theta + I
sin Theta this can be proven using the
tailor series of e s and cosine and it
works because the symbol I squares
to1 now the B Vector Sigma X Sigma y
also squares
to1 this is easily shown using the
properties of the sigmas in Matrix form
it squares to the negative of the 2x2
identity Matrix which I'm writing as
this fancy number one because of this we
can also use Oilers formula to rewrite
its exponential so if we exponentiate
Theta times the generator G gxy we can
move the factor of -2 so that it's part
of the
angle using Oilers formula we get cosine
of theta / 2 plus the XY by Vector * sin
of theta / 2 we also put an identity
Matrix in front of the cosine since
we're dealing with 2x two
matrices now cosine is symmetric so we
can forget about the negative sign in
its input and s is anti- symmetric so we
can move its negative sign out in front
so given this Oiler formula we can sub
in the matricies combine the cosiness
and SS into exponentials using Oilers
formula in reverse and get this Matrix
this is the su2 Matrix that rotates a
spinner in the XY
plane we can get the y z and ZX rotation
matrices using similar Oiler style
formulas the only difference is the
choice of B Vector in front of the sign
term these are the three su2 rotation
matrices for po Spinners in three
dimensions as an exercise you can show
that any Matrix of this form is unitary
so its inverse equals its Herm Mission
conjugate as a hint you can remember
that the Herm Mission conjugate of a b
Vector just swaps the order of the
sigmas so to sum everything up for the
2x2 represent ation of the su2 Lee
algebra we can either view the
generators as matrices as Clifford
algebra by vectors or as unit
querian and we can exponentiate these to
get su2 Le group members which we can
view as matrices Clifford elements from
the spin 3 group or as
querian so something worth noting here
is that our SO3 rotation matrices on
vectors rotate using using angles of
theta but the corresponding su2 matrices
rotate with angles of theta / 2 the
factor of 1/2 comes from the 1/2 in the
su2 Lee algebra generators we needed
this factor of 1/2 to make sure the S
SO3 and su2 Lee algebra commutation
relations were the
same in the case of SO3 rotation
matrices if we rotate by an angle of 2
pi we just get the identity Matrix this
means that if we rotate a vector by 2 pi
the vector doesn't change which is what
we
expect now if we take our su2 rotation
matrices and rotate by an angle of 2 pi
we actually get Negative identity
matrices so if we rotate a poy Spinner
by 2 pi we get the negative version of
that spinner it takes a rotation angle
of theta equal 4 pi to get Iden
matrices so Spinners require a rotation
of 4 pi to come back to their original
position the reason for this is that the
su2 Le group is the double cover of the
SO3 Le group remember su2 is shaped like
a three-dimensional sphere with matrices
plus u and minus U located at opposite
sides rotating by an angle of 2 pi takes
us from plus u to minus U U another
Rotation by 2 pi takes us from minus U
Back to plus u completing a full
rotation however to get S SO3 we draw a
line through plus u and minus U and
project them to the same point which is
a rotation Matrix R in SO3 rotations in
SO3 cannot tell the difference between
plus u and minus U and as a result s SO3
is shaped like half of a three sphere
where wandering off the edge immediately
teleports you to the opposite Edge as a
result a rotation of 2 pi will bring you
back to where you started so in SO3 we
only need a rotation of 2 pi to do a
complete
rotation so to sum up this video so far
we saw that the 3D rotation group SO3
has no 2x two representation or spin 1/2
presentation we needed to look at its
double cover su2 which had the same Lee
algebra to find the spin one half
representation that rotates
Spinners now let's go through a similar
procedure for the lorence group s so
+13 which is the set of rotations and
lorence boosts in four-dimensional
SpaceTime which also excludes
Reflections in time and
space recall the lorence group keeps the
SpaceTime inter interval with one plus
sign and three minus signs
unchanged the inner product of a pair of
space-time vectors requires this Matrix
called demon kovsky metric with one plus
sign and three minus signs along the
diagonal this is usually denoted by the
Greek letter
Ada if we change coordinates using a 4x4
Lorent transformation matrix Capital
Lambda the vectors will each transform
with Lambda inverse
which means the menovsky metric must
transform with a pair of lambdas to
balance out the change and keep the
SpaceTime interval formula in variant so
Lorent Transformations Capital Lambda
are defined by Lambda transpose a to
Lambda equaling
Ada so the standard representation of
the S plus 13 Le group is the set of 4x4
real matrices that leave the in kovsky
metric invariant have determinant one
and whose upper left Matrix entry is
greater than
zero we find the generators of rotations
are traceless and
anti-symmetric and the generators of
boosts are traceless and
symmetric there are six basic Lorent
matrices in 4D space time three
rotations which exchange two space
dimensions and three boosts which
exchange one space and one time
Dimension I'm writing the boosts with
these minus signs since boosting your
frame in the plus X direction will cause
vectors around you to have their X
components become more negative I
neglected to include this minus sign in
some of my previous
videos in video number nine of this
series we found we could also write a 4D
SpaceTime Vector as a 2X two complex
Matrix that I decided to call a vile
Vector this is Lorent transformed by a
double-sided transformation using SL2 C
matrices which are the 2x2 complex
matrices with determinant one for every
s so+ 13 Matrix there are two SL2 C
matrices plus L and minus L that do the
same lorence
transformation so SL2 C is the double
cover of s so plus
13 now what do the generators in the Lee
algebra SL2 look like since SL2 C Le
group matrices have a determinant of one
we can use this theorem with Matrix
exponentials to immediately conclude the
generators are
traceless now because su2 Le group
matrixes were unitary their generators
ended up being
anti-mission but SL2 C leue group
matrices are not required to be unitary
so there is no requirement that their
generators are anti Herm
Mission looking at a general 2x2 complex
Matrix if we force it to be traceless
this means Delta equal Alpha this leaves
us with three free complex parameters or
six real
parameters these correspond to the three
B vectors and the three vectors in the
Clifford algebra
cl3 these six matrices form a basis for
all 2x two traceless complex
matrices the B vectors which are anti-
hermiss generate the three
rotations and the vectors which are Herm
Mission generate the three
boosts as a reminder these are the
commutation relations for the S so +13
Lee algebra these should be the same
commutation relations for the SL2 C Le
algebra we saw earlier in this video
that the rotation generators needed a
factor of - 1/2 in front of the B
vectors to make these commutation
relations work out for the Boost
generators we must also put - 1/2 in
front of the vectors to satisfy the
commutation
relations you can pause if you want to
see the proofs that these commutations
work out or try to work them out
yourself this is the JJ commutator the
KK commutator the first set of JK
commutators and the second in set of JK
commutators now we've already seen that
when we exponentiate the bi Vector
generators we get 2x two rotation
matrices that rotate
Spinners and now when we exponentiate
the vector generators we get 2x two
boost matrices that transform Spinners
notice that these boost matrices use
hyperbolic trig functions this is
because the Clifford algebra vectors
Square to + one instead of minus1 and so
the Oilers formula tailor Series has a
bunch of plus signs which give us
hyperbolic trig functions instead of
circular TRG
functions since the formulas for
rotation matrices involve by vectors
taking their hermiss conjugate flips the
bi Vector order and gives the inverse so
the rotation matrices are
unitary since the Boost formulas involve
only vectors which are hermiss all the
Boost matrices are also her
Mission so the generators of the Lee
algebra SL2 C can be interpreted as
matrices as bi vectors and vectors from
the Clifford algebra
cl3 and also as by vectors from the
SpaceTime algebra
cl13 if we use this mapping here between
the sigmas and the
gamas these bi vectors in cl13 can be
thought of as the equivalent of querian
but for four-dimensional
SpaceTime we can also interpret the SL2
C lead group members in these three ways
as well either as SL2 C matrices as
members of the cl3 Clifford algebra or
as members of the spin 13 group in the
Clifford Algebra
cl13 I talked about spin groups in video
12 in this
series so we've discovered the spin 1/2
representation for 3D rotations which is
su2 matrices and the spin 1/2
representation for 4D lorence
Transformations which is SL2 C
matrices there are some key differences
between su2 and SL2 C that I'd like to
explore one big difference is that su2
only has a single non-trivial 2x2 matrix
representation
but SL2 C has two non-equivalent
non-trivial 2x2 matrix
representations which are called the
left and right
representations to understand why
SpaceTime has both left and right spin
1/2 representations we need to do a
parody
transformation I talked a little bit
about this in video
9 a parody transformation is when we
send all spatial directions to their
negative version
so it's a bit like reflecting the
universe in a three-dimensional
mirror let's see what happens to the 2x2
XY rotation Matrix under a parity
transformation a parody transformation
causes both X and Y vectors to get
Negative signs which cancel with each
other in the XY by Vector so the XY
rotation Matrix and rotation matrices in
general are unchanged under a parody
transformation this is also true for the
su2
generators this makes sense because
rotating X into Y is equivalent to
rotating X into
y now let's do a parody transformation
on a Boost since the Boost formula only
involves a single Vector it does result
in a sign
change we can move this sign change into
the hyperbolic sign since it's
anti-symmetric and we can introduce a
negative sign into hyperbolic cosine for
free since it's
symmetric we now see that a parody
transformation on a Boost results in a
boost with the negative hyperbolic angle
in other words this is a boost in the
opposite
direction the Boost generators also
change sign under a parody
transformation this makes sense since if
we have a boost in the plus X Direction
reflecting the universe in a mirror will
make it look like the Boost is in the
minus X Direction
instead so we see there are two spin 1/2
representations of SL2 C the original
which I'll call the left chyal
representation written 1 12 comma 0 and
the version where the boosts are
reversed which I'll call the right kyal
representation written 0 comma 1/2
although some sources use the opposite
naming
convention exponentiating these SL2 C
generators gives us left chyu and right
chyal SL2 C Le group
matrices we can swap between the left
chyro and right chyal SL2 C matrices by
taking the Herm Mission conjugate and
then the
inverse for rotations the SL2 C matrices
are unitary and so Herm Mission
conjugates and inverses are the same
thing so the left and right versions of
the matrices are equal for boosts the
SL2 C matrices are permission so the
dagger does nothing and so the left and
right versions of the Boost matrices are
inverses of each
other these two representations are not
equivalent because we cannot swap
between them using a change of spinner
basis I proved this in video 9 which is
linked in the description
we can take a left chyro vial spinner
and a right chyro vial spinner and take
their direct sum which means stacking
the two spinners on top of each other
the direct sum of their left and right
SL 2C transformation matrices would be a
combined 4x4 Matrix in Block diagonal
form so that the left Matrix transforms
the left spinner and the right Matrix
transforms the right spinner this is a
new represent resentation which is the
direct sum of the left and right
representations the 4x1 column spinner
is called a direct spinner we can split
up a direct spinner into the individual
vial Spinners using these projection
matrices
here these can be written in abstract
form using the direct matrices written
in the chyal basis where this term here
is often written as gamma 5 for short
the next difference between su2 and SL2
C involves the tensor product of their
representations I've shown in previous
videos that the tensor product of two po
Spinners can give us a 2X two po vector
and the tensor product of two vial
Spinners can give us a 2x2 vile
Vector I'm going to take this vial
vector and separate out the time
component which is just a scale identity
Matrix this is separated from the 3D
spatial po Vector which I'm writing as
V now let's do a rotation on this vile
Vector using a pair of unitary su2
matrices after breaking up W into time
and space parts and distributing we can
move U past the identity Matrix and
cancel it with UD dagger since for
unitary matrices UD dagger equals U
inverse the result here is that the
spatial XY Z components of the vector
transform under a 3D rotation with su2
matrices and the time component of the
vector doesn't transform at all so it
behaves like a
scaler now let's try this again but this
time doing a general lent transformation
with a general SL2 C Matrix L we can
move L past the identity Matrix again
but it does not cancel with l dagger
since in general SL2 C matrices are not
guaranteed to be
unitary this basically means that the
time component doesn't neatly separate
out from the space components since a
boost can potentially cause time and
space to mix with each
other this means that a Lorent
transformation does not always cleanly
separate into a 3D vector rotation and a
scalar component that does not change we
must treat the 4D SpaceTime Vector as
one
object since the tensor product of a
left and right vial spinner gives a 4D
SpaceTime vector and each spinner
transforms with its own SL2 C Matrix we
can think of 4D SpaceTime vectors as
transforming with the tensor product of
a left SL2 C Matrix and a right SL2 C
Matrix if we Loren transform a vile
Vector to a new frame and Carry Out The
Matrix multiplications we can set the
Matrix components equal to each other to
get four equations which can then be
Rewritten using a 4x4
Matrix this 4x4 Matrix can then be
Rewritten again as the tensor product of
a left SL2 C Matrix and the inverse of a
right SL2 C
Matrix now the entries of a vile Vector
Matrix involve the sums and differences
of SpaceTime coordinates but we can
easily change coordinates to The
Standard Time XY Z coordinates using
these formulas which translate to this
Matrix and its
inverse putting all this together we can
see this gives a 4x4 s so +13 Matrix
that lorence transforms a 4D SpaceTime
vector and this s +13 Matrix is
ultimately just the tensor product of
left and right SL two c matrices along
with a change of
basis this representation of the lorence
group is denoted like this or just as 1/
12 comma 1 12 so in SpaceTime the vector
representation is really just the tensor
product of two spinner
representations so even though a direct
spinner and a 4D SpaceTime Vector both
have four components direct Spinners
transform with the direct sum of the
left and right spin 1/ half
representations and SpaceTime vectors
transform with the tensor product of the
left and right spin 1/ half
representations the last thing I'll talk
about in this video is how the su2 and
SL2 C Le algebras are connected by
complex numbers when looking at the 2x2
representation of the SL2 C Le algebra
the three rotation generators are
anti-mission and square
to1 and they form the Lee algebra
su2 however if we multiply them by
netive I we get the three boost
generators which are Herm Mission and
square 2 +
1 so we can think of the six generators
of SL2 c as being made of two copies of
su2 combined using the direct sum one
ordinary copy of su2 for the rotation
generators and another copy of su2
multiplied by plus or minus the complex
I to get boosts the plus or minus sign
determines whether we get the left or
right spin 1/2
representation we call this the
complexified version of
su2 so with the ordinary su2 Lee algebra
we combine the generators using real
scaling
coefficients but with the complexified
version of su2 denoted with this C
subscript we can scale the generators by
complex scaling
coefficients since SL2 C is the direct
sum of su2 and I * su2 we can complexify
both sides and see that the
complexification of SL2 C is equivalent
to two complexified copies of
su2 we can absorb the complex I inside
the second su2 since it's complexified
anyway so complex coefficients are
allowed this leads to an interesting
trick with the
generators we previously defined the SL2
C Le algebra in terms of rotation
generators the J's and the Boost
generators the
K's in the commutation relations the J's
and K's get mixed
together now I'm going to define a
change of basis to the generators that
I'm calling A's and
B's I'm going to rewrite the J
generators using the axis they rotate
around instead of the plane they rotate
in and I'm going to drop the time T
index from the K
generators now I'm going to define the a
generators as J + I k/ 2 and the B
generators as J minus I k/ 2 where I've
matched the indices of the J's and K's
in each form
if we write out the commutation
relations in this new basis the A's and
B's cleanly separate out into a pair of
commutation relations where the
commutators of the A's and B's with each
other is zero these A and B commutation
relations look exactly like the su2
commutation relations so in this way the
SL2 C Le algebra is sort of like a pair
of su2 Lee algebras
since this change of generator basis
involves scaling by the complex I this
means SL2 C and both copies of su2 have
been complexified so in this way the
complexified SL2 C Le algebra is the
direct sum of two complexified su2 Le
algebras